Guide to the Boyte Family Papers, 1941-1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Boyte Family papers 1941-1981
Boyte Family
14.8 linear feet Extent: circa 11,100 items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.00152
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
A portion of the Harry C. Boyte Series is restricted until August 16, 2002.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Boyte family papers, 1941-1981, were donated to the Special Collections Department from 1967-1982 by Harry C. Boyte and Sara Evans Boyte.
Harry C. Boyte
1945, April 26 Born, Washington, D.C.
1963-1964 Founder, Duke-Durham chapter of Congress of Racial Equality
1964-1965 Field Secretary for Southern Christian Leadership Conference in North Carolina, Georgia, and Florida
1966, June 5 Married Sara Margaret Evans of McCormick, S.C.
1967 Received B.A. with distinction in Psychology from Duke University, Durham, NC
1967-1968 Attended University of Chicago Divinity School
1968-1970 Community organizer, Operation Breakthrough, Durham, N.C.
1970-1971 Editor, ACTION newspaper
1971-1975 Member of the founding body and National Interim Committee of the New American Movement
1976-1981 Member of the National Board and Executive Committee of the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee
1977-1978 Program advisor, Field Foundation
1978-1979 United States correspondent, Tempo magazine
1980 Published The Backyard Revolution: Understanding the New Citizen Movement
1980-1981 Senior Neighborhoods Policy Analyst, New Careers Training Laboratory, City University of New York
1981- Director, Citizen Heritage Center
Mr. Boyte, a freelance writer, has one son, Craig and one daughter, Rachel. He is the author or coauthor of numerous articles and books about left wing political and social concerns.
Harry G. Boyte
1911, June 26 Born Charlotte, N.C.
1936 Married first wife, who died the same year
1942-1944 Served abroad as Assistant Field Director, then Field Director for American Red Cross Foreign Service
1944, Jan. Married Janet Chatten in Evanston, Ill.
1944-1945 Assistant Chief of Personnel Administration for Red Cross Service to U.S. Armed Forces in Washington, D.C.
1946 Executive Director of American Red Cross of Greater Atlanta
1948-1959 Manager, Atlanta chapter of American Red Cross
1959-1962 Involved with civil rights organizations in Georgia, North Carolina and Virginia
1962 Directed community relations project for school desegregation in Prince Edward County, Va., for American Friends Service Committee
1963-1965 Employed as Special Assistant to Martin Luther King, Jr. for Southern Christian leadership Conference in Atlanta, Ga.
1965 Director of "Operation Dialogue" program for SCLC
1966 Employed as Technical Assistance Officer, Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, Atlanta, Ga.
Mr. Boyte is a member of the Society of Friends. He has one son, Harry Chatten Boyte, and one daughter.
Collection Overview
The Boyte Family Papers, 1941-1981 (bulk 1968-1977), chiefly contain printed material, including photocopies produced for meetings, conventions, and other group activities; periodicals, flyers, brochures, pamphlets, posters and booklets; correspondence; and reports, minutes, notes and other organizational records. Also included are drafts of essays and articles, photographs, notebooks, and audio tapes. While useful for a study of political and social activism and community organizing in post-World War II United States at local, regional and national levels, the collection contains little on the personal lives of the Boyte family. The collection focuses on the careers of Harry C. Boyte, political organizer and writer, in the 1960s and 1970s, and to a lesser extent his father, Harry G. Boyte, in the 1950s and 1960s. Social action organizations represented prominently in the collection include the New American Movement (NAM), the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC), and the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC).
Harry C. Boyte was involved in the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee and New American Movement, a national socialist organization with a Chapel Hill-Durham, North Carolina chapter. He was a member of the National Interim Committee for NAM, a steering committee for local groups. Literature from these and other groups with which Harry C. Boyte was affiliated, such as ACT in Durham, the New University Conference, the Southern Student Organizing Committee and Students for a Democratic Society is located in the Subject Files of the Harry C. Boyte Series. Together with publications in the early 1970s from other groups in the Printed Material subseries, these files represent issues including the Vietnam War and conscientious objection, socialism, feminism, labor rights, civil rights, gay and lesbian rights and the impeachment of Richard M. Nixon.
Harry C. Boyte wrote regularly for NAM and other socialist publications on socialist theory and organization. Drafts of some of his articles, along with correspondence containing critiques by his associates can be found throughout the NAM and DSOC files in the Harry C. Boyte Series. Correspondence in those files and in the National Democratic Left Relations folder between Boyte and his associates contains discussion of the implementation of socialist theories in contemporary American society. These exchanges were conducted more formally through Discussion Bulletins, contained in the files.
Papers in the Harry C. Boyte Series also relate to local organizing efforts in Chapel Hill and Durham, N.C., concerning health care, welfare, industrial safety and inflation. The information is contained in folders titled ACT, Health Care, Occupational Health, People's Association for a Cooperative Commonwealth, Utilities and Tenants' Rights. A small amount of material relates to student activism at Duke University and the University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill.
There is some material on the women's movement and the career of Boyte's wife, Sara Evans Boyte, who received a Ph.D. in history from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and became a professor of women's history. She was involved in a Chapel Hill women's group called Lollipop Power, a folder for which exists in the Harry C. Boyte Series. There is also material scattered through the NAM files about the Charlotte Perkins Gilman chapter, a socialist feminist group. Examples of feminist literature can be found in the Printed Material subseries and in the Robert P. McMahon Series.
Harry C. Boyte's father, Harry G. Boyte, left the American Red Cross to work in race relations. Eventually he was appointed the first white man on the staff of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference under Martin Luther King, Jr. Boyte's job search is documented by correspondence in the Harry G. Boyte Series. Contacts included the American Civil Liberties Union, the American Friends Service Committee, the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), the National Urban League, SCLC, the Southern Conference Education Fund, and the Southern Regional Council. The letters provide background information on Boyte's previous experience in Civil Rights projects. While on the staff of SCLC, he headed Operation Dialogue. There is material in the Correspondence and SCLC files of this series about this program intended to foster interracial communication.
Correspondence in the Harry G. Boyte Series also covers the later years of Boyte's Red Cross career and his initial involvement in desegregation efforts in Atlanta. He served as chairman of HOPE, Inc. (Help Our Public Schools) and as Executive Director of the Greater Atlanta Council on Human Relations. He was also instrumental in organizing an Atlanta chapter of the Unitarian Service Committee. The bulk of the Education files of this series is comprised of material relating to Harry G. Boyte's work for the American Friends Service Committee.
There is material in the Clippings, Correspondence and Racial files of the Harry G. Boyte Series regarding civil unrest in Monroe, N.C., in the late 1950s and early 1960s. During his short stay there, Boyte and his family hosted Freedom Riders and lent support to local NAACP leaders. Racial files include material relating to other Civil Rights programs and events in North Carolina and Georgia conducted by groups such as the Southern Regional Council, Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee and SCLC. There is also some literature from CORE in a separate folder.
Robert McMahon was associated with Harry C. Boyte after becoming a member of the Chapel Hill-Durham chapter of NAM. He was also involved in the local chapter of the New University Conference and the Chapel Hill Peace Center. While a student at the University of Virginia, McMahon served as President of the Newman Student Federation, and as Chairman of the Southern Student Organizing Committee between the years 1967-1968. The Robert P. McMahon Series contains information on the organization, planning and programs of these two groups. Some documentation of his political involvements can also be found in the Harry C. Boyte Series.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Boyte, Sara Evans; Social action; College students -- Political activity -- North Carolina; College students -- Political activity -- Virginia; New American Movement (organization).; Democratic Socialist Orgnizing Committee (U.S.).; ACT (Durham, N.C.).; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.).; New University Conference; Southern Student Organizing Committee; American Friends Service Committee; Southern Christian Leadership Conference; Socialism -- United States; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975; Conscientious objectors; Civil rights; Women's rights; North Carolina -- Race relations; Segregation -- Virginia; Political participation; Community organization; Boyte, Harry Chatten, 1945-; Boyte, Harry G., 1911-; McMahon, Robert Patrick
Contents of Collection
- Harry C. Boyte, 1959-1981 and undated (bulk 1968-1976)
  Arranged in Subject Files and Printed Material subseries. About one-half of the Subject Files consists of files, 1970-1982, on the New American Movement. This section consists primarily of typed correspondence and printed material, in equal amounts. Printed material includes drafts of published and unpublished articles, political statements, Discussion Bulletins, booklets, pamphlets and flyers. Also includes organizational records in the form of reports, resolutions, minutes, newsletters, meeting and discussion notes, announcements, agendas and convention packets. Other materials include several notebooks, loose notes, and training manuals. The remainder of the Subject Files consist mainly of a wide variety of printed material produced by left-wing political groups such as flyers, newsletters, typed copies of articles and speeches, fact sheets, booklets, pamphlets, reprints, conference information and reports. Correspondence, mostly to and from Boyte, is scattered throughout. Serials are filed in the folder of the producing organization if a folder exists.
  The remainder of the serials are arranged alphabetically by title in the Printed Material subseries. General printed material is arranged chronologically. A portion of this series is restricted until August 16, 2002.
  - Subject Files
    - ACT, 1968-1971, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Africa, 1964-1975, undated
    - American Friends Service Committee, 1959-1975, undated
    - Asia, 1975-1976
    - Billy Graham Day, 1975
    - Boyte, Sara Evans, 1966-1975
    - Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors, 1962-1973, undated
    - Chapel Hill-Durham, 1969-1976, undated (Box 2)
    - Chapel Hill Peace Center, 1973-1975, undated
    - Christian-Marxist Dialogue, 1961-1968, undated
    - Conference on Radicals in the Professions, 1967
    - Correspondence, 1971-1979, undated, (2 folders)
    - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, 1973-1976
    - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, 1977-1982, undated, (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - Draft, 1965-1975, undated (Box 4)
    - Duke University, 1964-1975, undated
    - Economics, 1963-1975, undated
    - Election Laws, 1971-1974
    - Energy, 1973-1974, undated
    - Farmers, 1973
    - Grape-Lettuce Boycott, 1965-1972, undated
    - Gulf and Shell Boycotts, 1973
    - Health Care, 1971-1975, undated
    - Housing, 1960
    - Human Rights Party, undated
    - Indians, South Dakota, 1973-1974
    - July 4th Coalition, 1976
    - Latin America, 1965-1975, undated
    - Legal Defense Fund, 1969-1971, undated
    - Legal Papers, 1972
    - Lollipop power, 1970-1974
    - Midwest Academy, 1974- 1979, undated (Box 5)
    - National Campaign to Impeach Nixon, 1973-1974
    - National Democratic Left Relations, 1972-1979, undated
    - National Interim Committee for a Mass Party of the People, 1973-1975
    - New University Conference, 1968-1970
    - New American Movement, 1970-1972, Apr., (3 folders)
    - New American Movement, 1972, May-Dec., (5 folders) (Box 6)
    - New American Movement, 1972-1973, Aug., (6 folders) (Box 7)
    - New American Movement, 1973, Sept.-1974, Mar., (7 folders) (Box 8)
    - New American Movement, 1974, Apr-Dec., (6 folders) (Box 9)
    - New American Movement, 1974-1975, Aug., (6 folders) (Box 10)
    - New American Movement, 1975, Sept.-1976, (6 folders) (Box 11)
    - New American Movement, 1976-1979, (6 folders) (Box 12)
    - New American Movement, 1980, undated, (6 folders) (Box 13)
    - New University Conference, 1968-1971, (5 folders) (Box 14)
    - New University Conference, 1972, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Occupational Health (NAM), 1971-1973, undated
    - Peoples Alliance for a Cooperative Commonwealth, 1975-1979, undated
    - Pictures, 1951, undated
    - Radical Historians' Caucus, 1969-1977, undated (Box 16)
    - Radicals in The Professions Conference, undated
    - Record, Crisis in the Nation, 1960s
    - Southern Conference Educational Fund, 1963-1975, undated
    - Southern Organizer's Conference, Greenville, S.C. (Sept. 4-5, 1971), 1971, Mar.-Sept, undated
    - Southern Student Organizing Committee, 1963-1967, Apr., (3 folders)
    - Southern Student Organizing Committee, 1967, May-1969, undated, (3 folders) (Box 17)
    - Students for a Democratic Society, 1962-1968
    - Students for A Democratic Society, 1969, undated (Box 18)
    - Tenants Rights, 1972-1973
    - Union for Radical Political Economics, 1972-1974
    - University of N.C. Student Strike, May, 1970
    - Utilities, 1972-1976, undated
    - Vietnam, 1965-1975, undated, (3 folders)
    - Welfare, 1971-1975
    - Youth, 1961-1969, undated
  - Printed Material
    - General, 1955-1972, (5 folders) (Box 19)
    - General, 1973-1979, undated, (6 folders) (Box 20)
    - Serials, A-G, (5 folders) (Box 21)
    - Serials, H-Pe, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - Serials, Pf-Z, (5 folders) (Box 23)
  - Subject Files: Restricted
    - Cooperative Commonwealth Project, 1980, undated (Box 24)
    - Correspondence:
      - 1971-1980, undated
      - (Private), 1971-1978, undated, (2 folders)
    - Human Rights, 1974-1976, undated
    - New American Movement, 1971-1973
    - New American Movement, 1974-1975, undated (Box 25)
    - Unity, 1976-1978, undated, (2 folders)
    - Miscellaneous, 1972-1979, undated
- Harry G. Boyte, 1944-1975 and undated (bulk 1962-1965).
  Chiefly Subject Files. Contains typed reports, correspondence to and from Boyte, clippings, speeches of Civil Rights leaders, press releases, a small amount of legal papers, and printed material. Printed material includes newsletters, brochures, booklets, announcements, annual reports, typed essays and information produced for meetings and conferences. Administrative records consisting of memos, minutes, agendas, budgets and correspondence which passed through the Atlanta SCLC office. Some correspondence is addressed to Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Arranged chronologically in Correspondence files and alphabetically in Subject Files.
  - Correspondence
    - 1944-1968, undated, (4 folders) (Box 26)
  - Subject Files
    - American National Red Cross, 1946-1959, undated
    - Appalachia, 1964-1975, undated
    - Biographical sketch, 1963, undated
    - Clippings, 1942-1968, undated
    - Congress of Racial Equality, 1961-1965 (Box 27)
    - Education, 1954-1966, undated, (4 folders)
    - Legal papers, 1955-1969
    - Pictures:
      - Harry G. and Janet Chatten Boyte with American Red Cross and Family, 1945-1950, undated
      - March on Washington, Aug. 28, 1963
      - Southern Christian Leadership Conference, including Martin Luther King, Jr., undated
    - Racial, 1957-1975, undated, (6 folders) (Box 28)
    - Racial, undated (Box 29)
    - Southern Christian Leadership Conference, 1957-1966, undated, (5 folders)
    - Miscellaneous, 1945-1959, undated
- Robert P. McMahon, 1965-1975 and undated
  Includes records of the Newman Student Federation in the form of correspondence to and from McMahon, notes, position papers, and printed material such as reprints, pamphlets, newsletters, reports and resolutions. Several notebooks with personal and organizational notes. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Subject Files
    - Newman Student Federation, 1966-1968, undated, (3 folders) (Box 30)
    - Notebooks, 1967-1973
    - People's Party, 1971-1974, undated
    - Pitt County Movement, 1971
    - Prisons and Prisoners, 1972-1976, undated
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1975, undated, (2 folders)
  - Miscellaneous, 1955-1981 and undated
    - Audio Tapes, undated (Box 31)
    - Pictures, 1963, undated
    - General, 1955-1981, undated, (2 folders)
    - Clippings, 1960-1976, undated, (2 folders)
- Oversize Materials
  - Harry C. Boyte Series
    - Subject Files:
      - Chapel Hill-Durham, 1974, undated (Box 32)
      - Gulf and Shell Boycotts, 1973
      - Health Care, 1972
      - July 4th Coalition, 1976
      - Latin America, 1974
      - National Campaign to Impeach Nixon, 1974
      - New American Movement, 1972-1975, undated
      - New University Conference, 1969-1972
      - Southern Student Organizing Committee, 1966-1971, undated
      - Students for a Democratic Society, 1966, undated
      - Utilities, 1972-1975
      - Vietnam, 1967, undated
    - Printed Material:
      - General, 1967-1969, undated
      - Serials, 1966-1973
    - Subject Files: Latin America (Opaperfolder OC:II:1)
    - Printed Material: General
    - Printed Material: (Box 33)
      - General, 1969-1976, undated
      - Serials
        - A-Gra, (3 folders)
        - Gre-Mr, (3 folders) (Box 34)
        - Mo-New Sol., (3 folders) (Box 35)
        - New York-Z, (5 folders) (Box 36)
  - Harry G. Boyte Series
    - Subject Files:
      - Racial, 1966, undated (Opaperfolder OC:I:8)
      - Southern Christian Leadership Conference, 1965
    - Miscellaneous, 1972 (Opaperfolder OC:II:4)
  - Miscellaneous Series
    - 1971-1973, undated (Opaperfolder OC:I:8)